Today I am on a journey through border country, land that was fought over for centuries, land where the ancient nations of England and Wales come together.
My travels will take me south through Powys and across the River Severn.
Then it's off to Knighton, along Offa's Dyke then through the Wye Valley to journey's end at Chepstow.
Along the way, I'll be looking back at the best of the BBC's rural programmes from this part of the world.
Welcome to Country Tracks.
Sometimes you have to climb up high to find out just why the border is, well, where it is.
And there you have it, the rolling Shropshire plains there, rising into the jaw-droppingly beautiful Welsh mountain ranges in that direction.
This land was fought over for centuries by ancient Britons, Normans and Saxons who all wanted to control it.
And in the 8th Century, the fearsome King Offa built his dyke.
Stretching from the North Wales coast to the Severn Estuary, it set a boundary which has lasted more than 1,000 years It's a landscape shaped by centuries of conflict and the spirit of the Borders lives on today thanks to those with a passion for its history.
Just watching these guys brings this whole landscape alive.
Now, Chris, you are a re-enactor, so tell me what's going on over here.
First of all, who are the Welsh, who are the Saxons?
The ones coming up here in the mail shirts are the Saxon patrol coming along the Dyke.
They're on the lookout for Welsh raiders.
Right.
And the Welsh raiders would be coming in to steal livestock?
Most likely.
All it needed was a bad harvest and they'd be going hungry at the end of the winter and they'd be looking to come across the border rather than to steal off their own countrymen.
But the Saxon patrol has spotted them.
And the Welsh aren't going anywhere without a fight.
I don't quite understand, I thought that Offa's Dyke was supposed to keep the two sides apart.
Offa's Dyke is more of a boundary.
It could be patrolled but it's 175 miles long, you can't defend it all.
If I was going to get involved in this, what side do you think I'd be on, the Welsh or the Saxons?
I think you'd be a Saxon - tall, blonde hair, with a name like Fogle, I don't think that's very Welsh!
Do you think I could do it in these clothes?
No.
But I've got some kit we could put on you.
First you're going to have to take that warm layer off.
I was liking that with the wind!
We'll start with the mail shirt.
Do you want to feel the weight.
THEY LAUGH OK, I have to put that on, do I?
You're now going to wear this, yes.
If you can get your arms right up into the sleeve holes first.
So you really did need someone probably to help dress you, you couldn't do this on your own.
You can get it on on your own when you're used to it.
OK.
How many links do you think are on this?
About 30,000.
Wow!
It actually doesn't feel quite so bad when it's on the body, does it?
The weight's distributed so it's not all in one lump.
I'd rather wear it and walk five miles than carry it for one mile.
BEN LAUGHS That sums it up, it's very heavy.
Right, so what next?
If I put your sword belt on.
If you can actually lift your arms up.
Then, when I put this on, this will actually take some of the weight onto your hips so it's not all on your shoulder.
So, how...?
Arms up.
Arms up higher.
Yes, sir!
How effective would this be at stopping a sword?
It will stop a cut, but it won't stop a sharp point like an arrow or a spear because that would break a link open and go through.
What else do I need, then?
Just one?
Just one because you won't need one on your shield.
And we'll pull the sword hilt round there so it's ready for you to get it if you need it.
That is quite a weight, everything that I've got there.
Wish me luck!
I'll pass you over to the Saxons now who will give you instructions.
Hello, fellow Saxons!
Hello, Ben.
'And every new recruit has to learn the basics, 'even if I'm stuck at the back!'
The Welsh that we're dealing with, are they an effective bunch?
They're very good skirmishers.
They are very wily and good at running about which is what we won't do today.
We are going to keep a tightly packed shield wall and we'll drive them back to Wales where they came from.
'But we struggle to push the Welsh raiders back even a few feet 'and it's a standoff.
'Pretty terrifying too, so I'm more than happy to take a back seat.'
On this journey along the English Welsh border I'm sticking mainly to the Welsh side.
But over in Shropshire, Adam Henson took to the skies for a birds eye view of border country.
The Shropshire hills have a distinctive character of their own.
Here on the Long Mynd, the sloping hills and valleys make it a haven for those wanting to take to the skies.
Mark, why are the Shropshire hills so popular for paragliding and hang gliding?
I think, Long Mynd, this area itself is one of the best in the UK.
We've got all the British records from here.
It's central, it's easy to get to.
The views are spectacular and people from not just locally fly here, from all over the UK, world wide it's got a really good reputation.
Are the Shropshire hills really good for the thermals, the uplift?
Absolutely fantastic.
The thermals obviously in springtime are at their greatest and they can go from a metre a second to 15 or 20 metres a second.
Really good lift and they work in the valley very well and the paragliders, because of the way they fly, can turn in them, like birds of prey.
It appeals to absolutely everyone, from climbers who are used to that sort of thing right through to people that have maybe disabilities who just want to have a go and experience the thrill of flying and so it has a massive appeal to everyone.
Well, it's got to be time for me to give it a go.
'I've chosen to have a lesson in paragliding.'
'After unpacking the wing, Mark and I do a spot-check.'
Make sure that there's nothing untowards in the glider.
'Next for some flight training.'
OK, so you always fly like this.
OK.
If you want to go right, you pull down on the right and push the left up.
Keep it to where you want to go and then you release back again.
OK?
When you come in to land, OK?
You then pull both down and then the glider flares, slows down and you can step down nice and easily.
'All sounds simple enough, 'just a small matter of getting airborne.'
That's it, hands up.
'So, a short run down the slope and up, up and away.'
'Well, perhaps not.'
'But after a few more goes, I start to get the hang of it.'
Well, that was just great.
I was off the ground, not far - took off like a beautiful buzzard, landed like a duck!
The wind conditions have to be right to fly off the top of Long Mynd.
If it's more than 15 mph, it's not safe for us to fly.
27, wow!
'It doesn't look I'll get to test out my new found flying skills today.'
Well, against all odds, Mark has told me now that the weather has changed and the wind has died down enough for us to get up in a tandem flight.
I've had my training, now I'm going for the real thing.
OK.
Arm underneath.
Both done up OK.
Better wish me luck!
Wow!
This really is a true sensation like a bird flying in the sky.
Amazing!
I'm exploring the border country between England and Wales and my journey takes me near Welshpool and across the River Severn.
There was a time when this river marked the border between England and Wales.
That was, of course before the native Welsh were pushed back into the hills.
So I've come to explore this stretch of water with a craftsman who knows all about life on the river.
My guide is Peter Faulkner and he's been making and paddling coracles for more than 20 years This looks a good spot here.
OK.
This is where the Offa's Dyke path follows the river.
Just over on the South bank, on the right bank, there's the actual Offa's Dyke itself so we're very close.
Perfect.
So this is a good place to cross.
This is a good place to cross.
So this is a famous Welsh coracle, made with a cow hide?
Yes, well, it's a beef steer from the butchers and it's sort of like a big drum really, onto a hazel frame with willow and then it's lashed on with a horse hair cord, the black and white cord you can see, that's plaited horse hair.
It's even got a tail!
It's even got the tail, yes, that's to ward off evil spirits.
Now, Peter, I have been in coracles before but not for many years and I was never particularly good at it.
'My first attempt was on Countryfile nearly a decade ago.'
No, no, no.
Man's a lunatic!
Can you give me a quick lesson again on dry land here?
A dry lesson.
Yes.
What's going to happen is the paddle will go like a pendulum.
That hand more or less stays there.
What you'll do is pull with a slight angle and pull back with a slight angle so it's like a figure of eight, very flattened...
So all I do is...
You're pulling with that and pushing with that.
It's a sort of a...
If I remember correctly, I didn't fall in the last two times.
Yes, I don't like cold water.
All right?
That's it, yes, and then the right foot in.
Yes.
And get yourself in the middle of the seat.
That's good.
There we go.
I'll just balance myself.
And I'll let you...
You're coming with me, aren't you?
Yes.
Thank goodness for that!
'I'm not that confident yet!'
So, again, it's that hand up.
Yes.
That's the right way, isn't it?
That's it.
Good, you're a brave man.
And then you...
Nice and steady, not too quickly.
That's good.
Right.
Then if you paddle then out across, as if you were going straight to the other bank.
Like this?
That's good, well done.
Yes.
What's the furthest distance you've done in one of these?
Well, on the Severn actually, 160-odd miles.
How long did that take you?
11 days.
I started at Llanidloes and ended up at Gloucester.
Do you think anyone's ever tried going across an ocean in these?
I know that a Welshman has been across the Channel.
Yeah, in a coracle.
That is very impressive.
I really don't want to fall in, that's my main thing.
Keep paddling toward the bank.
Like this?
Yes.
This is fun!
'Well, it seems coracling is a little like riding a bike.
'It all comes flooding back and I must admit 'it's nice to take our time and pootle around on the river.'
OK, thank you, Peter.
Now that is the way to cross a river - in a coracle.
Now, when actress Jean Marsh came to Offa's Dyke nearly 15 years ago, she did so in a rather more conventional manner.
Well, I've just climbed to the top of beautiful Burfa Hill.
Bit puffed!
Having left my car behind me at the bottom and eventually I will leave behind the beautiful country of Wales as well because this walk spans two different nations.
And from the top, I can see just about the whole five miles that I'm going to walk.
A bit intimidating.
It's very beautiful.
It also has wonderful historical content.
That's why I want to do it and one of the main parts of it is Offa's Dyke, the path.
And I'm now going to set forth and see if I can find it.
This circular walk will take me down to Burfa Farm and through the naturalist's paradise at Knill Wood.
Crossing the border, I'll find Knill hamlet and then up to the great prize, Offa's Dyke.
An easy stroll then back to Burfa and back to Wales.
It may sound a bit dramatic, but after all I am an actress, but I don't think I can live without walking.
It's a passion and I love walking everywhere.
I was born in London and I'm a Southerner but I feel not English, I feel a part of the whole.
Wherever I walk in Britain, I feel as if I belong there.
Coming out of the forest from Burfa Hill, now this is our first sign of civilisation.
Old Burfa Farm.
Looking at this lovely house now, it is difficult to believe that in 1960 it was so derelict, in such a state of disrepair that it was used as a hen house and there was actually an ash tree growing out of the living room.
This is Knill Woods and it's the sort of woods I really love to walk in.
One of the reasons I like walking on my own, I think best of all, is because animals are aware of you but they're not as frightened.
I don't feel at all solemn about my love of the country.
It isn't a serious thing, it's a joyous thing.
In fact, I mean, utterly inappropriately for my age, I leap about and skip and hop and jump.
Right!
We've now approached passport control.
This is a small step for Jean, but a giant step for mankind.
I am about to walk into England.
I really like having a walk that has many different points of interest, that's why I like going into Knill.
Cul-de-sac villages are always well protected and Knill has that sort of feudal air about it with all the houses looking rather similar.
For me the countryside can be just as holy as any cathedral.
An important and integral part of any walk is to visit a country church.
Knill has one of the loveliest.
Is the church always full of such beautiful flowers?
No, we have rather a special occasion at this time of the year.
We have something called the Open Gardens and we decorate the church just for this occasion.
The three main gardens in this hamlet, they're all open for the public to come round, for one weekend.
Knill Court was the original house here so I suppose you could call that the original garden.
So, Knill Court which was originally the manor house, the centre of Knill, then became a girls' boarding school and it was burnt down in the 40s.
Rumour has it that it was from illicit smoking, which reminds me of being a wicked little girl in the film The Belles of St Trinian's.
Of course, this part of the world does have a reputation for a little more rain than most!
But I don't mind.
Who cares about the weather when I'm walking in such beautiful scenery.
And none more than the steep climb up Knill Garraway.
Very steep, but worth it for the first glimpse of Offa's Dyke.
Offa was the 8th Century King of Mercia who felt it necessary to protect his nation from the Welsh borderland tribes.
So, he had this famous demarcation line built between England and Wales.
Well, this is it.
This is Offa's Dyke.
But obviously Offa had a bit of a problem here.
There's a theory as to why it's at such an extreme right angle.
The theory is that in those days there were two separate gangs of labourers hired.
Well, probably serfs in Saxon times.
And they started at separate ends and they met here and had to finish off at this odd extreme angle.
You can tell you're on top of a hill, this is Garraway Hill, and the weather is wild and wonderful.
Right, off we go.
It's so exciting for me to be walking along the very path that so many thousands have before me since, well, the year 750.
All those people going about their various businesses and now me, just for pleasure.
Well, that's it.
Three hours ago, five-and-a-half miles ago I started my walk and since then I've been through every terrain, every kind of weather, I've been through two different countries and I'm about to step back into the other one, way back up there where I first started.
Jean Marsh there enjoying a hop, a skip and a jump around Offa's Dyke.
I'm also continuing my border country journey along the Dyke.
I started out in Shropshire and nipped over the border into Powys.
As I travel further along the border, I want to understand more about how and why England and Wales were divided.
And I think Offa's Dyke could hold the key.
To unravel some of its mysteries, I'm meeting a man who knows this area like the back of his hand.
So what exactly is Offa's Dyke?
Well, Ben, it's basically a big bank and ditch which we're stood on here and essentially it separates England and Wales or what we now call England and Wales.
In fact, at the time that it was built, over 1,000 years ago, it would have been separating the Anglo-Saxon kingdom of Mercia, behind you there, and the Welsh kingdom of Powys on this side over here.
It relates to a time when the Anglo-Saxons are expanding across Britain and they're basically fighting with the native British people who are represented by the kingdom of Powys and they get to a point where the English king, Offa, of this period, decides it's time to draw a territorial boundary and maybe a partly defensive one and that's really what Offa's Dyke is.
It looks to me like it's more of a symbol than an actual physical defence.
I think that's a good point.
It's very big, it's massive.
Originally it would have been much bigger and a big ditch as well.
It would have been a big physical barrier but there were no soldiers patrolling it.
There are no forts, there are no roads.
It's completely different to something like the Roman Hadrian's Wall.
It is making a massive statement in that sense.
It's just about the power and will of Offa and it's saying, people might be able to cross it, might be able to clamber across it but, you know, you might be in trouble as well if you do that because the guy who's built this thing clearly means business.
And it must've been a huge physical undertaking.
Dug by spade?
Yes.
It's people doing this with the kind of tools you'd find in your shed.
I think we're talking of the labour, and it would have been labour, of literally thousands of people to construct this thing quit probably in a short period of time.
You've been studying Offa's Dyke for years, what does it mean to you?
I think the most evocative thing about it is it's really a symbol of the first emergence of the modern nations.
We're right at the beginning really of our modern era and we're just in the time when the languages we speak - be they English as we speak, or Welsh, as people still speak over there - begin to emerge.
And here is Offa's Dyke as a very physical symbol of that connecting literally to our cultural origins, to our ideas of being English and Welsh.
There's virtually nowhere else in Britain where you can go and physically stand on a remnant of that time.
I've just about reached the halfway point on my journey in the border town of Knighton.
Its Welsh name, Tref-Y-Clawdd, means "town on the dyke".
You can walk the National Trail all the way to Chepstow but, with night falling, I've arranged a lift.
Wow!
Now, THIS is my kind of taxi.
This is very cool.
Onwards?
Onwards.
While I continue my journey in this eye-catching set of wheels, let's go back a few years when I tried my hand at a very different type of four-wheeled transport.
You can't beat the tranquillity of the English countryside.
Yet here in Herefordshire, just over the hill there, there's a whole host of people getting an adrenaline rush.
This is now one of the fastest growing extreme sports in the UK with thousands of riders enjoying the freedom of the hills to perfect their jumps.
There are now more than 30 centres around the country.
It is a sport for everybody.
There's an element that everyone can try.
You can see kids as young as seven picking it up and starting to get on with it.
I've seen 55-year-olds riding down the hill.
And you're a course designer.
Is that right?
Yeah.
I do boardercross courses like the ones you can see in the distance, different types of jumps and freestyle setups like the slopes behind us.
Would you say this is a nice, safe environment for these guys?
Yeah.
We've designed this centre the same as all the other centres across the UK so that it is safe.
There is somebody at hand to do it and keep an eye on you.
It's in the countryside so there's fresh air and beautiful views.
What more could you ask for?
How do you go about finding your sites?
At first, we advertised in a country magazine for farmers with redundant slopes to take a look at our website and check out what the sport was.
We've been going to places like the Earls Court Smithfield Show where 100,000 farmers go through each year over the four days.
For farmers to go through and see mountainboards instead of a tractor or a combine was a very eye-catching thing.
We've had results from stuff like that.
For a slope that can only be grazed or mown et cetera, then, for a small amount of money - you're looking at around £5,000 to £6,000 - you can set up a centre and have it successfully running for a season.
It is a cheap way, a fun way, it brings a lot of life into the land and it makes a lot of people happy.
Right.
Now it's my turn!
All of you are going to start from this pole here, and we'll head down and try, if you can, to do a powerslide, stopping within the boxes.
Once you get to the blue poles, start doing the powerslide.
Once you get to the red poles, try and stop.
Does that make sense?
You're up first.
Brilliant!
Guys, is this going to hurt when I fall?
Yes.
No.
As long as I don't land where?
On your bum.
On my bum?
Keep your weight over the back of the board.
Stop yourself falling over by holding the front of the board.
And then I'm going to push the weight and pull that foot to spin it around, do I?
Yeah.
OK?
Er, no.
THEY CHUCKLE Wait.
Weurgh!
EVERY time!
Four years ago, Herefordshire farmer Roy Powell and his daughter Nicki decided to open up a mountainboard track to run alongside their pick-you-own farm.
Now they're attracting people from all over the country.
So whose idea was it to set up the mountainboarding?
My dad's.
Basically mine.
50 years ago I had terrific fun tobogganing down this hill and then about 20 years ago I looked into having a dry ski slope and unfortunately it was prohibitive cost.
So it more or less rested on its laurels until about 2001.
Surfing the net, farmers do surf the net...
..I came across mountainboarding and, luckily at that time, I found Maxtrack which specialised in setting up mountainboarding centres and that gave us, of course, a kick-start to this very venture.
And has it breathed new life into your farm, do you think?
Of course, yes.
Any additional enterprise, providing it's run reasonably well, is good and, of course...
It complements everything else we do on the farm.
You get parents coming up to pick fruit, drop their children at the boarding centre so they don't get bored, they're having fun.
The parents do what they want to do.
It works well.
So, how successful has it been?
It's been very good.
We've been very pleased with the way it's grown from year to year.
It's our fourth year this year.
We're seeing approximately 5,000 per season through the gates, um, and it is growing.
We're also hosting the national championship final later on this summer, which is really exciting.
Some of these guys behind me are world class riders, including World Champions Leon Robbins and his brother Austin from America.
The sport is attracting people from the States, Australia and New Zealand - all coming to Britain because it's the best place to do it.
Probably the best place in the world to ride is England.
They've got 40 places that you can go ride, slopestyle courses and boardercross tracks and all within three hours of each other so...it's a really concentrated place to come and ride.
Would you say that mountainboarding is still in its early stages?
Definitely, yeah.
It's been around for ten years.
It's still just now starting to catch on.
You see a lot of kids on the hill and they're into it and their parents are into it.
They have good places to ride now, so it's taken off.
Oooh!
Wahoo!
Well, we've had surfing, skateboarding, snowboarding... and now we have mountainboarding!
And, you know what?
This is BRILLIANT!
Woohoo!
I'm back on my road trip and getting to know my chauffeur, Andy Hazell.
He's a border-based artist and self-confessed magpie who collects all sorts of, well, junk and turns it into unusual art.
This old, retired hearse was a perfect canvas.
The funny thing is when I bought this from the undertaker in Anglesey, the other person who wanted to buy it was a goth rock band.
So, it's only me and goth rock bands who want to buy these things.
Why cars?
Why do you adapt cars?
Because cars were once sacred things.
Cars were things your dad used to polish on a Sunday.
And now, cars are throwaway items.
You can buy a car for £150.
It's the exact opposite of Pimp My Ride, where people spend a fortune turning it into something sexy and gleaming.
This is more about deconstructing the car, being playful with it.
Do you call yourself eccentric?
I'm probably seen as eccentric.
I don't think I am eccentric.
I think I'm perfectly normal.
And we're all odd?
Yeah.
And your workshop gives me the impression you're a bit of a Caractacus Potts?
I'm one of life's little magpies.
I do collect an extraordinary amount.
The best thing is, people know I collect things.
One morning, somebody had left me an inflatable boat outside!
RATTLING Was that something...?
Nothing important.
How would you like to think people received your art?
I say that my job is to put a bit of mystery and wonder back.
I'd say by the reactions we're getting, you're definitely getting "wonder"!
Confusion.
Yes.
Humour.
All of those.
Obviously it's road-legal...
It is, Officer!
I got stopped twice, once by Cheshire police, once by Tyne and Wear, driving this to Newcastle last December.
Presumably, they can't believe it is road-legal?
Neither can I!
And I'm in it with you.
I'm taking a risk.
Can we get up a hill like this?
Oh, yes!
Course we can!
I trust you.
You must get some wind drag, though?
There is a fair amount of wind.
Heading through Powys, we come to Presteigne and we're running low on fuel.
I'm glad you find that so funny!
Right, on to another petrol station!
The diesel pump is that far away.
The petrol pump is that far away.
The petrol pump doesn't reach by that much, so I'll take the spire off.
Lucky you brought the ladder.
Have ladders, have spanner.
This could be quite a long journey.
That's definitely a new one for me.
Have you ever seen a car that's had to remove its spire to get under your roof?
No.
We've had a few horse boxes that haven't fitted well!
But that's definitely a first.
What do you think of it?
I think it's really good.
I especially like the lights in it.
I'd love to see that at night.
At night, it looks great.
There we go, then.
Have a good day.
And you too.
Right!
Onwards!
On the road again, we soon enter the Wye Valley.
My journey started in Shropshire, winding along the border, through Powys, and will eventually bring me to Chepstow and the Severn Estuary.
This is certainly a very unique way to explore the borders and I've finally reached the Wye River.
Not long ago, John Craven came here for Countryfile and explored the Wye Valley all the way to Chepstow, which is where I'm heading.
On my walk today, I'm going to be straddling the border between England and Wales, because I've come to the Wye Valley, a place of limestone gorges and dense woodland, of historic towns and dramatic ruins.
The Wye Valley makes a remarkable claim - that it's the birthplace of tourism in Britain.
The Valley is an internationally protected landscape of great beauty.
It's formed by a 72-mile stretch of the meandering River Wye, from just south of Hereford, to the rocky outcrop of Chepstow Castle, where it meets the River Severn.
Down there, through the mist, is Monmouth.
I'm looking at it from a vantage point called the Kymin, 900 feet above sea level.
Back in 1800, the gentlemen of Monmouth built a monument here, a temple, to the Royal Navy and its victories.
They also built a banqueting house where, once a week, they would meet and dine in great style.
It became a local landmark.
Lord Nelson himself was invited here and he remarked on the splendid view.
No doubt he had a better day than this one!
One thing's for sure - he didn't use the kind of water transport I'll use for part of my journey down the river.
Before that, let's pop down to Monmouth and learn a bit more about the historic town.
It is pouring with rain now in the main street in Monmouth, but that's not deterring these people digging up a garden.
What's going on, Steve?
We had a chance to excavate here and because the archaeology of the street is so outstanding, we couldn't miss the chance.
What sort of things have you found?
That level we're at now is about 1300.
But beneath that, there's something like 5' of medieval floors, dirt floors, full of the remains of hundreds of years of occupation.
What was going on at about the time people are digging now?
This is really a hiatus in the street and in the country, because that level is just after 1300.
They were about to build a large house here and they were overtaken by the terrible floods and the Black Death, which stopped everything in the street for a long time.
What kind of things are you finding as you're digging?
Are you finding bits of pottery and things?
Yes, pottery and occasional coins, but not a lot here.
But we are getting very distinctive pottery of the early 14th century.
This is some of the pottery made in Monmouth.
What would this have been from?
A jug.
It's a medieval jug.
But it's decorated with different colour clays.
And that is distinctive of this period, just before the Black Death.
What about the most famous man ever to be born in Monmouth, then?
That's Henry V, of course, born in Monmouth Castle in 1387.
You've got Agincourt Square here.
And Glendower Street.
Owen Glendower, who was the great opponent of Henry V.
Does it always rain here?
It al...
Well!
You are in Wales, don't forget!
So, what can you expect, yes.
Yes, it's nice soft weather.
You've been paddling up and down this river for quite a few years now.
Yeah, quite a few!
Has it changed a lot?
It's changed...
The height of it has changed.
It's probably due to the water extracted from pump houses for domestic and industrial use.
This must be the most perfect way of watching wildlife on the river.
It is.
Wildlife...they don't perceive us as a threat.
Having passed through an area, we've left no mark on it.
How clean is it?
It's a clean river, probably cleaner than it's ever been, I would think, judging by the kingfishers, goosanders and cormorants you see.
There's otters too.
You never see them, but you see their tracks.
So, it's a nice, clean river to paddle along.
Sure.
Yeah, sure.
Oh, look, there's a kingfisher there, just left-hand side.
Kingfisher where?
Crossing the river.
I've got him.
Oh, there you go!
There he goes!
Wow!
It's a while since I saw a kingfisher so close.
What happened to this bridge here?
Well, this was a box section bridge and when they were salvaging it, cutting it, the guy this side was stood on it with oxy-acetylene and the foundations gave way and it fell into the river.
He was on it, they rushed him to hospital, I guess he was OK cos he came back and finished the work cos it's gone!
He fell in with the bridge?
He fell in with the bridge, yeah.
Lucky man.
It caused quite a stir in the town.
Well, that's enough paddling, now to the serious business of walking cos there's still about 12 miles to go to Chepstow.
I got off the canoe on the English bank of the Wye and now I'm crossing on this old railway bridge back into Wales again.
Over there, in England, is the village of Redbrook.
In days gone by this was an important industrial area - there was lots of tin and iron about - but no trace of that left anymore.
The sun has come out.
Goodness knows for how long, but what a difference it makes to this area, cos it brings out all the different shades of colour, doesn't it, Andrew?
It does, yes.
It's a very special place indeed.
The river here cuts a fantastic limestone gorge, cloaked on either side by semi-natural ancient woodlands, which have existed here since the last ice age.
We have a high density of wildflower meadows, the river itself supports an array of protected species, it really is a very special place.
And how difficult is it to keep it looking special?
It's a challenge for us, certainly.
We work with all the various organisations, the land owners, the community groups, they're the ones who make a change and influence how the land looks and it's working with them that we achieve that goal.
You must get involved in quite a lot of bureaucracy with England on one side and Wales on the other.
Yes, it does present an administrative challenge for us, cos we aren't just international, we also go into three government regions and three different counties, so all of the various partners are often duplicated or even triplicated.
What's all this about the Wye Valley being the birthplace of tourism?
It all started with the Reverend William Gilpin, who took a tour down the River Wye in the 1770s.
From that he wrote a book entitled Observations On The River Wye.
It was a great success and inspired many people to come to the area, including people such as Wordsworth, Turner and Coleridge.
This wonderful viewpoint is called Whitestone.
When William Wordsworth did his grand river tour of the Wye he climbed all the way up here and wrote these lines.
Though changed, no doubt, from what I was when first I came among these hills, when like a roe I bounded o'er the mountains by the sides Of the deep rivers and the lonely streams Wherever nature led, more like a man Flying from something that he dreads than one Who sought the thing he loved.
These must be some of the most beautiful, most impressive ruins anywhere.
What's left of Tintern Abbey.
It was only the second Cistercian abbey to be build in Britain - work started in 1131.
Eventually there were about 100 of them and, like all the rest, Tintern was knocked about a bit by Henry VIII.
So who exactly were the Cistercians, then?
Well the Cistercians were Benedictines, a breakaway group who felt that the order wasn't following the rule of Benedict in quite the way it should have been.
So they set themselves up in isolated places like Tintern as an agricultural community - well, they had to, they had to fend for themselves, make their own food.
They did it very well, didn't they?
Amazingly well, yes.
They actually constructed the landscape.
In fact, today the landscape is still is often quite Cistercian.
Henry VIII's men didn't do a very good job of demolishing this place, did they?
I mean, it's much more intact that most ruined abbeys.
Indeed.
I think the reason for that is that the lands went back into the estates of the Earl of Worcester, who was a Catholic lord on the King's Council, and since his chantry chapels were here with his family tombs, he didn't really want to see that all disappear, so he to make some effort to destroy part of the abbey and then he just locked it up.
It was a very remote area.
So the King didn't really know...
No, the King didn't know what was going on.
So he just took the roof off, really.
That's indeed what happened, yes.
Well, here I am at journey's end.
I started in a border town - Monmouth - and I'm finishing in one - Chepstow.
And over there is it's famous castle.
The castle is Chepstow's pride and joy.
In fact, it's the oldest surviving stone fortification anywhere in the country.
It was built during the time of William the Conqueror and it still dominates the town.
The weather on my little trek has been far from perfect, but the buildings and the scenery have been fantastic.
The Wye Valley is certainly a great place to go walking and canoeing.
Travelling solo once again, I've also arrived in Chepstow, which reveals the most dramatic sight yet of the border between England and Wales.
I've explored border country from the Shropshire plains to the Welsh hills, Starting near Oswestry, over into Powys and through the Offa's Dyke town of Knighton.
Then it was on through the Wye Valley and to Chepstow - and a truly awe-inspiring structure, which straddles two nations.
The Severn Bridge.
People have been crossing the Severn Estuary since Roman times, but it's a perilous journey.
The tidal range is the second highest in the world, beaten only by the Bay Of Fundy in Nova Scotia.
There are two bridges over the Severn Estuary, very similar in design and less that four miles apart.
The older one of the two was completed in 1966 as an alternative to the old ferry service, which could only carry 17 cars at a time.
Since the day it opened, the old Severn Bridge has carried over 300 million vehicles.
Oddly, it's two bridges in one, because it spans both the Severn Estuary and the River Wye.
I took a walk on the Wye side with bridge general manager Jim Clune.
Obviously the main Severn Bridge is behind us.
We're technically on a different bridge.
Why have you brought me here?
Well, the Wye bridge is actually the border between England and Wales.
So, basically that's almost like an island just behind us and this is a different river?
This is the River Wye, yes.
So we're just about to cross into Wales just over here, is that right?
Yes, as we speak we are crossing the border between England and Wales.
The thing I notice most is it's very noisy, very windy and very wobbly.
Is this all normal?
Yes, it is.
This is a steel structure and steel is a living material, so it is designed to move and it is absolutely safe.
Where we're walking is sort of a public path, is it?
People can walk along here?
Yes, this is a public right of way for pedestrians and cyclists.
Though not the most pleasant place to come for a walk.
As somebody who runs this route, I can tell you it can be absolutely invigorating, depending on the wind speed.
And the wind must really howl through here.
Yes, it does.
This bridge is occasionally closed during the winter when the wind is very strong, but the design of the deck is such that we can't actually install wind shielding.
We are incredibly privileged, cos we're in a lift heading up one of the towers of the Severn Bridge.
Hopefully, shortly I'm about to get the most fantastic view between England and Wales.
This really is a real privilege to come up here.
I've been to the Severn Bridge a few times over the years, but never... up to the top of the tower!
How incredible is that?
So, obviously, we've got Wales over there, and England over there.
Quite extraordinary.
Travelling the border between England and Wales, I've seen how it's been raided, protected and fiercely fought over.
Standing here, I see one border which no-one could contest - Britain's longest river as it finally meets the sea, splitting two nations along the way.